this is my this this issue's probably a
slightly a little bit more nebulous it's
linked to his railing against political
correctness and the dangers of political
correctness and the impact that it can
have on freedom of speech because
freedom of speech is not about being
free to say things that people agree
with but being free to say things that
people don't agree with and that is
likely to upset or offend them and the
ability to do that is necessary in order
to have difficult conversations about
difficult complex topics you have to run
the risk of offending people in order
for thinking to take place he makes the
point of thinking is rarely done on
one's own very very few people have the
capacity to actually think to doubt to
question to really seek to undermine the
presuppositions on which the argument is
based which is necessary for actual you
know actual progress actual thinking
actual new ideas to take place and so
this leads onto his a dialogue about the
proper roles of the left and right in
political discussion that the right
fights for the validity of hierarchies
hierarchies are necessary in order for a
group to undertake activities
hierarchies are going to be created and
that they are necessary and that they
are good if you like the role of the
left is to highlight the fact that
hierarchies dispossessed lots and lots
of people at the bottom and to be fair
to mr. Peterson he does acknowledge the
fact that the hierarchies do dis possess
very large numbers of the people at
bottom and and dispossessed with zero
and equally he acknowledges that getting
from zero to something is very very much
harder than getting from something to
more as I said before I think he under
plays the extent to which our systems
are responsible for that and kind of
over plays the impersonal forces like
the preeto distribution but anyway well
I've already talked about that what I
want to talk about here is the left
the left versus right thing as it
relates to the road to totalitarianism
and so I've kind of laid the groundwork
and so those are the proper roles of the
left and right and that we know the
right has gone too far when they start
talking about racial purity or
superiority or whatever but we don't
really yet have an understanding of
where the left has gone too far in that
despite his decades of research and
writing on the subject he doesn't think
that he fully understands what the
warning signals are when we're going
down the left-hand road to
totalitarianism so I kind of take issue
with the whole meta suppositions on
which this this discussion is based
because as far as I'm concerned and
listen I'm nowhere near as well-read or
it's well educated on the topic as he is
and I'm quite willing to accept the
possibility that I'm missing something
here however as far as I can see
totalitarianism is totalitarianism it
isn't it is an attempt by the state to
absolutely control the doings of its
people right down to you know right down
to the last detail and in order to
accomplish that needs to have very
strong structures and institutions in
place in order to surveil and coerce its
population to doing things it might not
otherwise wish to do that's that that's
what I see totalitarian and now whether
you go down the left or the right
doesn't seem to me to make any
difference and for someone who is so
meticulous about exploring and seeking
truth uncovering layers and layers of
you know removing veils and veils in
order to get to the truth I find it
extraordinary that his answer to the
question of when is the right context is
a simplistic as racial hatred whatever
superiority whatever it may be and you
know it seems to me that the road of
totalitarianism is when the state starts
to exert
excessive control over the thoughts and
actions of its people and it seems to me
that whether that goes via the pervert
you know via fascism or via communism is
absolutely irrelevant both of these
things are giant state structures
controlling its people through a
combination of brainwashing and coercion
and you know I really really don't
understand what the distinction is that
he's trying to draw and I can understand
to a certain extent even though it
doesn't jive with anything that he
actually says but given the vehement
anti left
start that he takes the anti extreme
left stance that he takes and kind of
dismisses as tat well that's all right
they're not talking about racial stuff
therefore they're not too far off the
map that seems to me to be a little bit
of a distortion not to mention a gross
oversimplification state control over
its people is manifest in its desire to
control the narrative which as far as I
can see through mainstream media the
state does a very good job of
controlling the narrative and telling us
what we ought to be thinking and making
sure it knows what its citizenry is up
to and you know given revelations from
Snowden and others as to the extent to
which we are under constant surveillance
is particularly our web presence you
know our social media presence our
searches search histories etc etc and
the degree to which we are surveilled
and profiled primarily for marketing
purposes and nothing more sinister than
that but nevertheless the apparatus
exists for the state to control and I
don't understand why he's not more
worried about these things I really I
really don't understand why he doesn't
see us as being further down the road
towards totalitarianism than we are and
this whole left-right thing seems to me
to be a distraction from a permanent on
unelected state apparatus which is
taking us further and further down the
road
totalitarianism and for someone who is
as well-informed well-read and well
versed in the subject as Jordan Peterson
is I find his oversimplification of this
kind of stuff to be a bit suspect I also
think is what's the word extremely
offhand dismissal of anything leftist or
Marxist is is also somewhat simplistic I
mean socialism at its core is about
society rights in the word socialist in
its in the word it's about creating a
functional dynamic healthy vigorous
society and having skin in the game is
essential to that you know work the the
whole labor for money contract is an
aberration to most clever classical
economists you know if you don't have
skin in the game you don't care about
what you're doing and you are on the
road towards eventual impoverishment
because the assets the real value
remains in the hands of the owners is
not distributed among everybody else
anyway I'm going slightly off-topic here
my real issue is with the left-right
distinction when it comes to
totalitarianism as far along so
totalitarianism mr. terris Arianism and
and and what color it may have started
out as is irrelevant that whole color
thing is a distraction Trump is a
distraction brexit is a distraction now
five-year Lee elections are a
distraction from the reality of what's
going on that we are under tighter and
tighter and tighter control by this
apparatus which is not the state as we
understand it not the elected
representatives of the state as we
understand it